Federal Theatre Project Collection
Federal Theatre Project Collection
1936-1938
Federal Theatre Project (U.S.)
.25 linear ft.
Collection of play scripts, bibliographies, photographs, from the United States Work Projects Administration's Federal Theatre Project
2515821
Biographical History
The Federal Theatre Project (FTP) was sponsored by the Work Projects Administration (WPA) to fund theater and other live artistic performances in the United States during the Great Depression. The FTP's primary goal was employment of out-of-work artists, writers, and directors; its secondary goal was to provide affordable entertainment for poor families and encourage the dramatic arts. It was established August 27, 1935 and Vassar theatre professor Hallie Flanagan was appointed its head. Although initially Flanagan touted the FTP as being "free, adult, and uncensored," the federal government soon became uneasy at the progressive and left-wing themes evinced by many FTP productions such as their Living Newspaper.
Many notable theatre figures of the time participated in the FTP and it launched the careers of many others, including Arthur Miller (who turned down a $250-a-week job offer from Hollywood to write for the FTP at $23 a week). Orson Welles, John Houseman, Martin Ritt, Elia Kazan, Marc Blitzstein, Arthur Arent and Abe Feder all became established, in part, through their work in the FTP.
The FTP's funding was terminated in 1939, due in no small part to strong feeling in the Congress about the FTP's political stance.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Federal Theatre Project Collection contains a variety of publications of the Federal Theatre Project's Play Bureau and National Play Bureau, among them play scripts, bibliographies of foreign-language plays, and lists of suggested plays in particular categories. There are also photographs from performances.
Arrangement of the Collection
The publications are in alphabetical order by title.
Related Material
has considerable material relating to American radical and left-wing literature. Please refer to for a complete list of related collections and material.
Our Rare Books collection also has rich resources in this area; please refer to, where a search with the subject "radicalism in literature" will bring up a lengthy list. Of particular interest may be the following titles:
Living Newspaper, by the Federal Theatre Project (U.S.)
Federal Theatre, by the Federal Theatre Project (U.S.)
Play Bureau publication, by the Federal Theatre Project (New York, N.Y.). Play Bureau
Publication, by the Federal Theatre Project (New York, N.Y.). Play Bureau
Subject and Genre Headings
Radicalism; Dance and theatre; Hudson, Arthur Palmer -- Folk songs of Mississippi.; Clugston, Katharine, b. 1892 -- Barnum returns, or, The new American museum.; Reuben, Isidore -- Suggested repertory of continental plays.; Chadbourne, Philip, Suggested repertory of modern continental plays.; Liss, Joseph, 1911- -- Spanish miracles and moralities available in English translation.; Liss, Joseph, 1911- -- Early Spanish one-act plays in English translation.; Carlyn, Rose -- Plays for a marionette theatre.; Federal Theatre Project (U.S.); United States. -- Work Projects Administration.; United States. -- Works Progress Administration.; American drama -- 20th century.; Drama -- Bibliographies.; Folk songs -- Mississippi.; Political plays, American.; Radicalism in literature.; Socialism and theater.; Theater -- Political aspects.; Theater and state.; Bibliographies.; Photographs.; Scripts (documents); Theater programs.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, various times
Accruals
On an irregular basis, as new items are purchased
Inventory
- Bibliographies
  - Anti-war plays for community theatres, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Early Spanish one-act plays, available in English translation, compiled by Joseph Liss, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Early Spanish one-act plays, available in English translation, compiled by Joseph Liss, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Plays for a marionette theatre, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Spanish miracles and moralities, available in English translation, compiled by Joseph Liss, 1937? (Box 1)
  - Suggested repertory of modern continental plays, ca. 1936 (Box 1)
  - Suggested repertory of classic English plays, ca. 1937 (Box 1)
- Plays
  - Barnum returns, or, The new American museum, by Katharine Clugston, 1936 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - One Third of a Nation, New Orleans, Jun 1938 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Folk Tunes from Mississippi, Dec 1937; tunes and words to more than 45 folk songs (Box 1)